this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
I see radio brings you relevant the detailed discussions about software engineering topics at least once a month.
thanks to our audience and the partners listed on our website for supporting the podcast.
[Music]
okay, welcome listeners to another episode on top engineering radio.
today we talked with Reena consoling about distributed scrum. so welcome, lynnie.
Thank You Morgan.
would you like to introduce yourself to our listeners?
yes, that's that's fine.
uh yeah, my name is Renae. I'm a software engineer.
from my education, so I did computer science, then I did my PhD in management science.
and now for some time, I'm a professor in global software engineering at the Delft University of Technology.
it's a part-time position, so for one day 1/2 day a week.
and besides that, I am working as a scrum coach, distributed scrum consultant, CTO at a company in the Netherlands. scrum Donnell.
cool, so we are going to talk about the distributed scrum.
can you tell us or introduce us to what do you mean with exactly distribute its to grab?
yeah, that's that's a good question.
in fact, because in many cases you're on your research side you're blinded by your terminology.
and then I thing is to say this, that if there's some research has been done in in Sweden.
to let's say get something on the terms.
I mean everybody using some terms.
so Dalia Smitty and Klaus Rowland has led some research.
and at that level to really define the terms.
so we've distributed in my research.
I mean you know say software engineers that are working together in a team.
well they're not on the same location.
but of course then the question is what's not the same location.
but let's say if they are in the same building you could call that collocated.
and in this case we would call it distributed or dislocated.
meaning there is at least I would say substantial travel time to reach one side to the other.
and when substantial substantial, I would mean it's more than more than half an hour more than an hour drive. okay, so what do you think?
some kind of outsourcing and offshoring also belongs to some kind of tributes Graham?
or would you think it's a different thing? yeah, exactly.
you talk about distributed development normally people are talking about offshoring development.
or in my case you know my research on global software engineering.
so when people are distributed over over continents across time zones thousands of kilometers.
however if you look at the research.
and some leading work has been done by Thomas Allen.
he says in the building construction, but he did some empirical research. and in that they detected and in fact.
and when people are more than thirty meters just more than thirty meters apart from each other.
that the chance that they run into each other and have let's say unplanned interaction drops to a very low level.
so I meaning that when people are more than thirty meters apart from each other.
they it doesn't really matter where.
but if it's hundred meters it's hundred kilometers or it's a couple of thousand kilometers.
they don't meet each other anyway.
okay, and and you know also referring to distributed scam scrum in the term of across companies.
or within one company but different locations.
so having this kind of contracting between companies is that also topic or or not really?
yeah, well wouldn't we talk about distributed software engineering.
we're just talking about the location we're talking about it about a distance.
if you would let's say scrum master.
so if we move to the agile a way of working.
distribute the scrum would would in my case be only the geographical conditions.
but then of course you get other definitions that whether you do is stuff in source or you outsource.
so it could be that you say well we have outsourced distributed scrum.
and we have in-house distributed scrum. okay, I see.
but the distribution is really a geographical term. mmm, I see.
all I know about scrum is it's really invented and more mostly suitable for one team.
sitting together in in in one office maybe in one room.
what do you think are the biggest pain points when working with distributed scrum?
yeah, exactly that's that's that's a good thing to ask.
especially because it's its start from which which already we started with.
and that's also let's say in the research community.
I'm part of the international conference global software engineering the ICGC dot org.
and also in that community you see let's say two flavors.
and then the two two kinds of ways to look at it.
so half of people say well this this scrum and this agile is exactly working very nicely in co-located teams.
that are interacting very frequently and work together let's say in an well sort of structured way.
but let's say not a communication is structured and because of debt.
and when they're close to the business owner they achieve incredible results.
and they achieve hyper productivity.
so that part of the community says well you must be completely stupid to use an approach.
which let's say works very fine when you're co-located to apply this in a distributed location.
because well you you you're abusing something which is intended for co-located in a distributed setting.
that's that's half of the of the audience of half of the people on the conference.
the other half of the people saying well you know if we're talking about distributed development.
the main problems coming from distance our communication control and coordination.
well, and if agile approaches are very strong in one thing then it's arranging the communication to control on the coordination.
so you use scrum or you use agility or agile methods as a solution to a problem.
and the problem is that the distribution creates problems in communication control coordination.
and you try to fix that with within and at your way of working.
and when I when I give presentation of the and I say say well some small kids and the kids are born.
and small kids they only look with one eye they have two two eyes. but one of these eyes they're not really using.
so they are merely were watching one dimensional.
and when they find it out these kids the kids see double and they have have problems with walking.
what I do then they they take a bandage and I put it on the well working eye.
and because of that they forced the sick I order the lazy eye.
they forced their eye to function as well.
and in fact that's a little bit what you do when you start working with scrum in in distributed development.
so you're using an approach which let's say is really very strongly building on info formal control.
and informal communication and coordination in a setting where that's that's exactly exactly difficult. so and that's the other half half of the audience.
and that's let's say more a part of the ordinance that I feel connected to.
I see lots of advantages we've using scrum in a distributed setting.
because scrum is exactly solving those points which are weak in a distributed setting.
but how does it look like in practice?
so an Instagram you facilitate communication with with a daily scrum for example.
where all the people stand together and talk for 15 minutes each other.
and I couldn't imagine that that is easily possible and it is tribute a team.
even with different time zones and things like that right?
but let's say one of the the starting points of course with agile scrum is let the team figure it out.
the the team consists of smart well-educated people.
that are pretty well able to find a way in which they get things working.
so scrum is let's say one of the rhythm isn't is in in fact the daily huddle.
where you have the daily scrum meeting about 15 minutes.
in which the team aligns their work sets goals for the day.
and make sure that they are working on a on a good planning.
and that the impediments get detected and get get best at that same day.
well of course when you do this distributed that's a challenge.
the challenge is when you do a co-located meeting then it's very very obvious that it works.
so how do you get this working in a distributed setting?
on the other hand the meeting has a purpose.
and because of the purpose you solve a couple of problems.
so the team will always find ways to deal with for example the daily the daily stand-up.
and what I see in in in distributed teams that are let's say distributes on long distances.
and in time zones what they what I most of time do is they start do the daily hurdle.
they do the daily scrum at the start of the latest team members.
so for example when you work with India you see that let's say when it's 8:30 or 9:00 o'clock in in Europe.
that's the time for the day huddle.
that's when the complete team sits around or stands around ideally a screen.
with a Skype action or some other kind of a video conference.
there is really daily stand-up what you see them besides of it.
most of the time is that let's say the team members that start the earliest.
or in the example let's say the India team members they still have the the the wish to align their work among themselves anyway.
so what you don't see that you see a kind of small daily huddle occurring at the team that starts at first.
and then the others join in and then they have let's say the team huddle.
and what happens if the time zones are so widely distributed?
like say you have people in in in Japan and India and Europe in North America.
so that you don't don't be able to find any exact time spot where all the people can sit together.
yeah, well also for this is let the team figure it out.
you know the daily stand-up is not there to just stand up.
I mean you know and if there's let's say a timing problem.
or it is really let's say an infeasibility to really have everybody stand around and have a short meeting to line stuff.
okay, well then you have to find other ways of dealing with that.
the the main purpose of the daily huddle is to make sure that let's say everybody is is aware of the status.
every everybody is clear what others are doing.
and that there's let's say a daily heartbeat in which let's say problems are detected and impediments are busted.
that's the purpose.
and any team how distributed it is over which kind of exotic time differences are there able to solve it in a way that fits them.
um okay, I see.
but just one more question regarding communication here.
in this case my observation is that if people are distributed they tend to communicate last.
and if they are sitting together in one room.
so it's it's it's it's happens more often that people talk to each other when sitting in front of each other.
then if you have to pick up the telephone or need a Skype call or whatever.
so people tend to be a little bit lazy and getting lazy about this communication thing.
and that is I guess something that you really would like to avoid.
how do you you try to avoid this laziness in picking up the telephone.
or communicating with people who are working on a different times though maybe different language different country.
okay, let's say that thing there's two two answers to your to your question.
first of all of course is indeed when people are distributed they they they tend to communicate less frequently. that's for one.
and that's also one of the reasons why I'm so in favor of using agile methods for example.
and then in my case most time it's it's scrum.
because everybody in the team is completely aware that if they don't communicate scrum will fail.
because agile methods rely and depend so heavily on informal and frequent communication.
that they completely fail when they don't.
so let's say it's the number one risk.
and while we are let's say as human beings have complete difficulty in doing many things in parallel at the same time.
we are all very good at focusing at the number one risk.
and that and if you also look for yourself to your projects in the past projects or our encounters.
rarely fail because of the number one risk.
because the number one risk is that let's say there are all kinds of actions.
everybody is focusing on them everybody's looking at them. so most of time it doesn't fail over there.
it always fails or the problems always come from the number three or number four risk.
and that's the benefit of using let's say agility in distributed teams.
that everybody is focusing on the number one risk.
and the number one risk if we don't act as a team if you don't communicate.
if we don't have let's say the frequent interaction our way of working will fail.
and we as a team will fail.
so that that's that's one one part of the solution.
so the fact that you use agility in distributed teams solves it already for a large extent.
on the other hand of course still there is no real collocation.
so you need to find ways and and tools can help in that way.
but also let's say just habits I can help for he'll will help in that.
to make sure that these awareness of the distance goes down.
and and I think I will get better to that later.
but let's say that the key to distributed development is in awareness.
so it's not the distance itself which is the problem.
it's the perception of the distance.
so it's not affected people are on the other side of the world working at the moment that's the problem.
it's a problem that you have the feeling they are far away.
so and there's technology that that can bring that closer.
and and of these new technologies is one thing I one I would like to pinpoint it.
and and and and give specific focus to.
and which is an American startup company which is called so koco.com s o co co.
and i don't know whether you've heard about the market or whether you've seen it.
you know okay well so coco it's really fun to watch because what they do in fact they provide a virtual office environment.
and not not not three-dimensional like in the Second Life or something.
it's more it's more two dimensional.
so it's it's a map of a company in which you see let's say a conference room with screens which you can share.
there are private offices where you can work and work on and work in.
and the point is that if you have here your headset up on and you have your microphone open.
just as when you normally are working so you list the music anyway.
so you have the that's I don't know anyway if you say something the people in the room.
so in the in the virtual room in so Coco they will hear you just like in a normal office environment.
if you speak out people in the same room will hear you and in the adjacent room they won't.
and the same goes in the Chicago office.
so you have let's say they create a kind of office awareness in which everybody can have the private office.
or they can share it officer which day which they work.
but still if you speak out people in the same room will hear you.
and they or and when they speak out they will hear you will hear them.
there are screens on the wall team screens where you can share information where you can work on together.
so this is an example of let's say a a tooling environment which creates the perception of a low distance.
and it's great and creates the perception whether people are working in the same room. and for my university research this is really interesting.
because of course from a factual perspective we cannot solve distance.
you know there is a there's there's 6000 kilometers to to the other side in India.
I'm not able to solve that but I can reduce the perception of that distance.
so when people have let's say the feeling or the the same level of awareness.
when they are dislocated when they are collocated we solve that.
and that's it that's it so Coco is an example of a solution to that.
and at the moment we are running an experiment in in the Netherlands with with with a company.
in which all people of the company and they are a very large distributed company.
they all work together in Chicago and the first results are really promising.
we are not solving everything of course say that there is still some dislocation.
but the perception of awareness reduces largely.
so they have the feeling they are much closer when they are working in an ER farm like that.
what are you observing with these first experiments and what problems remain with that tool?
well, it's it's most of time it's not in no it's not in the tool.
it's it's how you look at it.
for example if I demonstrate its first time and people look at it.
and I say yeah well but what can it do differently than for example Skype well and that's not the question.
yeah, I mean you know it's you shouldn't look at it from from a functional perspective.
you should look at it from let's say a perception perspective or from an awareness perspective.
so let's say if it creates a perception of distance - which is closer than when you have it originally.
so but of course you should use the tooling and that that's the point at the point of it.
but you did you have this tour you can start it up automatically when you're when your computer starts.
and we are I'm very happy with it for for example I have two PhD students which I work for now.
and I'm travelling around I'm only at university one day a week I'm at customers etc.
but we have just a policy within our team and the PC students are also dislocated.
they work at a company to work on University.
and we have this internal policy if you turn on your PC so cocoa starts up automatically.
and we have our own office space so we are there we can see there that we're there. we can ask a question to each other when it's necessary.
sometimes it's just to say hi how are you how was your weekend or good night I'm going home.
sometimes we don't talk at all during the day.
but still we have the awareness at the perception that were much closer then we're not.
because else we would have to call and then you interrupting or you send an email. and you have to wait for an answer.
but because we're in an environment which let's say gives us the same kind of awareness as an office environment.
the perception of distance and the feeling of distance reduces.
and I think that's that's the main you had the main the main the main hurdle to take.
and that's also let's say that the main goal in our research at the University of Delft.
is what I call that say create a virtual 30 meters.
I mean we have the yelling curve we have the the åland distance of 30 meters.
and of course we cannot fix the distance between so for engineers which we can reduce the perception of the distance.
so when people are working dislocated but they still have the feeling they are within 30 meters of each other.
we have let's say solve the large part of the problem.
would you also move the information radiators that are typically used in scrum.
and for example the task board into such a tool?
yeah, that's that's a nice question that you asked.
I mean the the tools in in scrum let's say and you call it a radius but let's say the scrum board etc they have a purpose.
and the main purpose of a scrum board is to have visual oversight and to visualize progress - let's say to say to managers who want to know what the program is.
we're not going to send you report come in look at the wall and you see our progress.
you see the tasks moving around you see the burndown going going down.
so that's how we how we deal with progress.
and that's the purpose to facilitate communication among the team that people interact.
you see when working with scrum that the scrum board becomes let's say the center of communication.
and that's the purpose.
as soon as you have sought to work distributed the one of the first question that comes up which tool are we going to use.
and don't don't misinterpret me it's not that I'm against tools.
but tools have the tendency to block communication.
so when we are working let's say with two locations I'd rather have a scrum board in each location.
and scrum masters that call each other three four times a day to make sure that the scrum boards are aligned.
I preferred that over the tool in which let's say people are just sitting sitting behind their desks.
entering the data into the into the tool and block the communication.
on the other hand of course when you were it's also handy when you have a tool environment.
so but as long as everybody who's using the tool is very much aware.
that the tool is not there to record the data in the information.
but the scrum board or the tool is there to felicitate facilitate the interaction.
then it's fine and they use it use it for that.
so what I often also see that they use a smart board is a for example JIRA on a smart board.
and then you have let's say the best of both.
on the one hand you have let's say the visualization where everybody can see it.
and at the same time it's easier to distribute to other locations.
because there's a database underneath which keeps it up to date.
there's on YouTube this is quite funny it is I think it was in Denmark but there's a group at Vodafone.
so if you type in a do to prefer the phone in an RFID scrum board.
they had an RFID scrum board made themselves which is connected to JIRA.
and let's say when you move the scrum cards over the boards they updated automatically in the background in JIRA.
and when somebody behind her desk starts to alter JIRA then the scrum board starts complaining.
that it's out of dates because the cards are not hanging on the right position.
it's a bit nerdy but quite funny.
they have a nice movie on YouTube on it where you can really actually see the Sprint progressing on on the board. cool, sounds funny.
yeah, we should we should put the link on the show now.
yeah, typical typical pet project for example for FedEx Day or something.
which is something fun to make over the weekend on.
I also saw teams were distributed they are trying to use actually.
the distribution to benefit from it.
in terms of let's say following this this kind of Conway's law.
where you have if you have distributed teams you will get a distributed system.
or when you have four teams let them build a compiler you will get a four pass compiler.
for example the eclipse team they're using the distribution nicely too.
put the or two strengths and the module boundaries and at the exact exact same points where the teams are distributed.
so that they have oh we have a module binary.
and this should be a good API between module boundaries.
then we put the two teams working on the client and it produces side of this body boundary in two different locations.
so that there is some kind of communication going on but less than if they're on side.
what do you think of this this way of using the distribution to build the system?
first first one is of course is that maybe not everybody in the audience understand Conway's law.
but Conway's law says something like the architecture of a system reflects the way the organization that created it.
meaning so when you have a system with which is built and you are organized yourself if three departments.
you will most of time see the three departments back in the architecture of the system. right, exactly.
well first of all it's des it's called Conway's law.
but first time I encountered it I did some research on it.
well it's a hypothesis it's not a law.
I mean there's there's hardly any evidence of this this law at least I haven't seen it.
but anyway it's it's logical it seems it seems logical.
that when you distribute groups and they try to not interact as much as possible.
that you will see that reflected in in the system.
so that seems logical.
and also when you work with let's say an outsourcing partner and then it may it seems logical.
that you will somehow find that back in the in the architecture of the system.
because indeed you would like to fix an interface and develop parallel to it and then do the integration.
but I think there's two ways to reflect reflect on on that.
first of all architects should serve you and it would serve should not serve development teams.
an architecture should serve the end-user hand.
it should you build software to create business value.
so the architecture is also serving that business value.
delighting customers responding to change fast.
and making sure let's say the systems we create the develop business value any when they are being used.
and it can be to create money but at canosa s save people's lives provide energy protecting environment etc.
so value is not necessarily economic value.
so that's one one thing.
so architecture should serve debt it should not serve development teams.
I mean so if you let's say have teams that work together.
and let's say just for a matter of easiness or to make it easier on themselves.
this construct an architecture they are making a basic floor.
architecture is not there to serve the team's architecture is there to serve the end-user.
that's the first response.
so that's why I'm also very much in favor of of let's say in the way.
as your team's deal with architecture by letting it emerged from the most valuable user stories.
because the most valuable user story is you take it first.
they can be much more dominant to the architecture.
so then the architecture emerges from that.
and not let's say from teams that say well it's easier for us to work together.
second thing is of course that you when you work in a way like that you are postponing integration.
and with the risk of pulling feedback to later point in in time.
and the third thing is of course I don't know how much software you have developed here Martin.
but it's always when things need to be changed.
it's always easier to request a change from the other than from yourself.
and that's always the problem then when it's teams it's you get an us-versus-them.
we want you to change something now we cannot you have to change etc.
well that doesn't serve the end-user either.
so that's one part of the one part of the exam of the answer.
is that when constructing teams please make sure let's say that they are let's not serving the teams.
but they're serving the architecture for the FIR for the system.
that's the first part of the question.
so and the second part of the answer is that if we look at the research on HR teams.
and on distributed HR teams you can also look at the work of Quito shown I'm Jeff Sutherland.
who did something a fully distributed scrum you you you you could find it.
there is that one of the as we see is that you put difficult issues within the team.
so it's an interface it could not be a technical interface but also the distance interface. for example put it in the team.
so when you have for example two scrum teams you have eight people on one location.
and eight people on the other location which is 16 in total.
that would mean two scrum teams.
so the easiest way say well okay then we have scrum team a on location a.
and scrum team Bianca on location B.
and it's easy these people can work on located they can interact with each other.
and in the end we do the integration that's a way to serve to solve that.
well if we look at the way that's been doing in practice and the evidence that's there. it's it indicates that that's not a very good solution.
because then there's a lower level of interaction between between the teams.
maybe even at some time distance etc.
so there will be some inter team problems.
if you let's say are able to construct it that the teams do not have to work together at all.
okay, well that that's then of course fine. but most the time it's not.
when you have two scrum teams working on the same system they need each other.
so then the best practice is to make sure that the teams are distributed.
so when you have done aids people on one location eight on the other.
you could create two teams with each let's say four people on one location or four people on the other location.
because then you bring the distance within the team.
and when you put the distance in the team people will work together.
and they are trying to solve problems because let's say they are dealing with the total problem.
and not the solution on the other side.
so that's the same thing when you would do the same thing when a technical system.
it would makes much more sense to bring also the the technical challenges within the team.
so bring them within the team in which they deal with that instead of fixing them.
because if then things change you yeah well you have the team structure there and you're not able to change that.
so I see that you really try to not avoid those communication problems.
but to face them and try to solve them within the team right?
I think that's that that's that's the core of scrum.
the core of scrum is not doing scrum or doing agile or having these meetings etc.
the course cry is moving towards hyper productivity.
and the only way you can you you can create hyper productivity and high value creation in a team.
is by structurally taking impediments out.
so you take the number one impediment which slows you down solve that.
and then promote the number two impediment to the number one.
and that you put on top of your list and you solve that.
so that's the only way of really improving continuously and really creating progress. so that's not a problem impediment to another problem.
it's not by by hiding problems you should let's say put them out in the open and solve them.
one of my favorite remarks is that that people say is that scrum is like your mother-in-law.
she comes into your house she finally points out all the stuff.
and all the things that are not okay but then doesn't do anything to solve them. and that's what scrum is.
and so it helps you to detect impediments but then you have to solve them yourselves.
so also within when you have let's say distributed teams working together there is problems.
distributed work is very hard.
it's much easier than that the best way to develop systems is half the problem owner.
or the business owner who wants the system in the same room.
with a small team of cross-functional skill developers solving this problem as soon as possible.
with an agile approach in which they take the the most valuable user story first.
get that done get that into use create value with that and then move on.
that's the most powerful way of working.
as soon as you start distributing to serve you think you had create problems with communication control and coordination.
those are impediments and those you need to solve says.
so as soon as you bring this distance within the team it will be one of them main impediments.
and they will solve it because they needed to to solve it to get better.
I think you you was referring to this role and scrum of the product owner.
where where the developers are getting back to them and asking questions and things like that. so typically in scrum you have this kind of.
oh you should have this kind of one product owner or at least this one voice to the team.
telling you what is important and it's planning questions.
how would you deal with it and it just be the team.
so where typically maybe the product owner is just maybe located in one location and not the other one.
or would you have a product owner in each location or what is your preferred way of dealing with it?
well first of all there's a few basic rules.
and one of the rules is you should never forget one team one backlog one product are.
so as soon as you start to distribute people over the team it says it's.
and the team is on to location it still holds one team one backlog one product on.
so that that's the one thing you should never break up.
and you see many cases solutions popping up and I don't know it's up to the team.
the team will find a way of working and I think that's the one the main thing that counts.
so I'm not the one who's saying this is a good solution that's a bad solution. the team should figure it out.
the one thing with you off soft or sometimes see is that they call this product owner proxy or scrum master proxy.
and it might solve some of the issues but it also has a danger in it.
because there is only one product owner.
so if let's say this proxy product owner really understands his or her role.
is able to align with the real product owner on a daily basis.
or maybe a couple of times a day to make sure that they are still on the same track and on the same line.
I think that could be it could look good good way to solve it.
on the other hand I mean the product owner is called product owner this owner thing is there.
and I mean any product owner who is responsible and is passionate about what he what he or she is doing.
is always able to help a team to solve their problems.
and it doesn't matter of the location. I mean I've been a product owner myself for a couple of years.
I have was traveling around and it was just the deal with the team.
of course I wish it was attending the meetings.
but even in the Sprint if they needed me the scrum master would call.
I would answer my phone independent of where I was what time it was.
I would answer my phone because the team can never wait for the product on.
and of course when they start calling me every five minutes in the middle of the night.
will think of some kind of solution.
but let's let's solve that problem then that problem will pop up in a retrospective anyway.
we needed a product on all the time in the midst of the night. and then we deal with that and we solve that.
instead of avoiding problems putting a product on a proxy.
with a big risk that there's no alignment with the real product owner.
and then at the end of the Sprint or another song or some other time a point of time.
product owner will see something which is not in line with the expectations.
so you're you're postponing feedback.
and postponing feedback is always a major impediment.
you know that's what we do agile for you know postponing feedback always shoots you in the back.
it always comes back to you at the point of time where you don't need it.
so it's not as I say you cannot have product on a proxies or solve something on a location.
but the big danger is there that you're postponing feedback.
so I'd rather have a product owner a single one on a location.
so then distributed team maybe put two developers of the team close to the product owner.
and put the other part of the team on the other location something like that.
but make sure that the team really understand what the product owner wants.
so keep the distance between product owner and team as close as possible. that would be my main answer.
I would like to ask you another question about distributed teams.
what happens if if you start with a distributed team?
typical if you start with scrum team you have some kind of team building.
and people will figure it out themselves.
if you have a distributed team it sounds to me a lot more difficult.
and a lot easier if people see each other in person then if they don't see each other in person again all the time. completely right.
you know one of the the best practices in distributed scrum is build around.
you know teams are not created by themselves.
I mean team building teams takes time takes effort and needs people to see each other.
one of the directors of a company that I I work with very frequently always says.
you know you have to be drunk once on one single location together before you are a team.
and and there's there's tears of truth in it.
I mean being a team is standing standing out to each other be willing to confront each.
having trust in each other.
a great book to refer that a work is the work of Patrick Lencioni.
who wrote this management book five dysfunctions of a team.
which he really shows a pyramid or five levels off of team building.
and five levels to really create a team.
and it all starts with trust.
if there's no trust you don't have a team.
and if you anybody who has been in a sports team or in a a social team or whatever T or a development team knows.
that if there's no trust you're not a team.
and building trust over long distances with Skype is of course much harder than to do it on a single occasion.
but I think that's one of the the wrong or one of the fallacies of off of our field.
when we talk about distributed development is that when we put we do co-located development.
people interact with each other all the time.
they have meetings have a talk meetings they they go for lunch.
they have evening chats take out cooking together they do all these kind of things together.
but when we start distributed them there's some kind of assumption we should never meet.
and of course it's that that's stupid.
of course you need to meet the problem is there's distance between it.
so you need to plan it more carefully etc.
but still you know I think you know within a team when it's distributed.
and you look to each individual there is somewhere between ten and twenty percent of their time.
they are still on the other location or interacting with other people on that location.
and also when I would start a scrum team which is it needs to be working distributed.
or at a company where I work for when we start with a new team or a new client.
where we create its distributed teams it's very easy. first two sprints one location we set the people together.
and it can be that the people from the Netherlands move to India or the or vice versa.
but let's say building a team and getting working practices together.
making sure that you can rely on each other that you trust on each other to keep each other accountable.
it's much easier to build a park or you know co-located setting. but nobody says that you cannot do that.
nobody says when you have a distributed team you have to be distributed all the time.
would you also recommend to do this kind of face-to-face meeting on a regular base?
yes, definitely.
it's what I said I think if you would look to the calendar of an of individuals in a software team.
they and I think that between ten or twenty percent of the time.
they should be on the location as close to the product owner as possible.
okay, that's that's let's say the ballpark figure.
and and that's that's often overlooked there.
when people start to make business cases for especially for Shore development they're only looking at cost.
well that's stupid.
I mean we are not in our field to reduce costs.
we are building software to create revenues or therefore the profits.
and we're there for the benefits and for the revenues not for the cost.
and when i when when there's taking a look at offshore we're just making this a very ballpark figure kind of comparison.
so we have to here on our location if a team of twenty and it costs so much.
so when we have the same team of twenty on offshore location it's much cheaper.
well that's a simplification of our fields which really will come back at you.
it will create much much problems because it's not a cost it's the value what's coming from her from it.
so if you distribute teams in your work out locate so you work in offshore setting.
you should do it for the proper reasons and cost should never be the one.
so people traveling from one location to the other should be effect.
the fact that people from one side visit the other and work with them should be effect.
and it should never be in the business case.
when you go to work offshore that you try to reduce costs on traveling.
or way that you try to reduce cost on team building.
or you try to reduce cost of people seeing each other.
people need to see each other to really work together.
and when they have done 20 projects together they have seen each other many many times.
they have been drunk many many many times maybe they need to see each other goes down.
but it's it's in that order.
it's it's not the fact that you say well we have this great team that's working on our location with ten people.
and they're working great together let's offshore the team.
and then expect that within one week they are on the same level as the co-located team.
what about different different cultures they have experience with distributed teams.
that are distributed across different completely different cultures?
okay, what culture is is is a separate topic.
I mean there's a lot of work done on that I made a Technical University.
so I'm not trying to repeat social studies.
one way we can deal with is the work of Hofstadter where he used these five dimensions of culture.
that's it that's a way to deal with it.
but the one thing I would like to say well their culture is it's a nice label.
I mean but culture is not that clearly defined and always present present it's a distribution.
you know you have people that are outspoken in India.
you have people that are never say yes or no in in the Netherlands as well. so it's it really depends.
you have national culture but also you have a company culture.
and there are some evidence that the company culture is much more dominant than the national culture.
and you even have a professional culture within the profession which is more dark more dominant than the company culture.
I mean culture is all about norms and about values.
things you think are normal or things that are proper and things are improper and things are good and bad.
you know that's the norm and the value system. and within a professional culture like software engineering.
there's a much more dominant culture of what's good practice and what's a bad practice.
or what's what's what's good software what's bad software.
which is much more dominant than the national culture where somebody comes from.
the only point is culture is the best excuse.
I mean if you are putting people in a in a cross-cultural setting.
of course there will be some experiences of that.
and there will be some expectations which which seem to be false.
if you're working with people in Asia who think it's it's more important to be polite than it is to be honest.
you should calculate with that you should know it.
and if you don't deal with it properly and then you might might get some surprises.
but culture and my experience is the best excuse for your own failure.
so if you don't arrange yourself yourself if you don't train people.
or if you don't let's like try to create a team.
and if you if you don't try to align a goals of the team and things fail. then you didn't do your work.
so what do you do then?
well then it's easy you blame it on the culture because that's not your fault.
so we talked a lot about this kind of distribution and how to get rid of the problems doing distribution.
sometimes you might could get the impression that you should avoid this tribute development at all.
to overcome all the problems and do you think that's true?
or do you think it's also feasible and usable for some kind of projects?
okay, yes. yeah, good question.
yeah, well of course when you started working distributed you introduced some problems that come forward from the distance.
so if you don't need to do it I would say don't do it.
but those of course very good reasons to think about distributed work or offshoring.
and one of the things the main reasons are the capacity.
so the fact that you can get much more people and expertise and well-educated people on your projects.
or when you're working then you get locally.
that's the main reason I think to go for distributed development.
second thing would be that you have a worldwide presence.
you you like to be close to your customers.
so when you have let's say a customers distributed over the world it makes sense to also do it.
to be close to your customers also have some development effort and people close to your to your customers.
and the third thing is it's time differences.
although time differences are let's say have some problems with it they also have advantages.
I mean you can do 24 hours of work if the work of Carmel on follow-the-sun software development.
well let's say people pass their work on to people in the new time zone that the starting their day.
and they passing on work all over the globe.
so that there's 24 hours of development work instead of only only 8.
also you have companies that give guarantees.
you know if you submit your or your books or your issues today.
we have solved them by 9:00 tomorrow morning.
because they have two people in a different time zone that are working while you are sleeping.
so I think those are the main reasons.
and for the but let's say I would say that the number one reason to consider distributed development.
is the availability of goods educate people.
and to give you an example in the Netherlands there's a very large shortage of educated people.
one of our customers even won a prize for the best people employment ads in the newspaper.
so they'd like to have some poor people and they had an ad in the newspaper.
but it won a prize for it they get no letters of applications to it.
but that well that on the side or if we look to we have a side in India here at Cramton l.
and we get let's say between 50 and 100 application letters per day.
Wow, doesn't mean we hire everybody you know.
but we have let's say every day we invite eight software engineers to talk to us.
and to see who they are and whether they would fit up our company.
we don't hire them all there are good people in it.
their people would say we don't fit our company culture.
but still you know it's a luxurious positions to be able to choose the people that work for you.
instead of being happy that there's one people applying for a job.
and I think that's that's the main the main reason.
if you like to solve the challenges of tomorrow.
and if you would really like to free the value which is there in IT systems and software products.
you need good people to build them.
and they're much easier to find and to hire in offshore locations and then they are in here.
yeah, I see there is there is a book you wrote it's called the power of scrum.
and it's not a typical scrum book because it's a novel.
yes, what why did you why did you decide to write a novel.
instead of it this kind of typical scrum book explaining what scrum is?
yeah, we want to book the power of scrum together with Jeff Sutherland and alcohol Sandberg.
and indeed it's it's it's a novel.
it's a kind of management fable.
it's tells a story about the CTO who misses his flight.
and here's a project him problems major customer.
and then he comes in contact with scrum and he doesn't understand it anything.
well there's nothing for me and etc.
well the main reason I did it that the first the first deployment of scrum that I did in the past. wasn't a company where I was CTO.
I was it I was a head of development.
I was controlling all the developers and they were on all on one location.
and they worked with this big waterfall planning of one year release.
which then of course always become one and a half years etc etc.
so I did a scrum deployment over there.
but I could do it because in the management board where I was sitting.
I just said to all my colleagues from sales marketing the CEO said leave me alone.
you know I have seen this before I know how it works just give it a time.
and I will prove you within six months it'll work.
and we had a tradition in that that come in that company that they used one year planning amongst.
the time it became one and a half half-year stuff was thrown away mid time a vision changed etc.
and what I did I we just introduced krump with monthly sprints and six months into iterations.
and the first the first release six months releases.
and the first release was let's say two weeks late because of two major books.
and the second release was two days late because of a so obviously a single or single book.
so I mean I could prove it to undo them immediately.
that we were able to create value that we will be able to release on time.
also in this first release when we were using we using scrum.
we tear down a complete list of issues from the help desk from the sales.
all kinds of questions that they could not get answered in the past years we solve them within six months.
so I showed value in this management team very very transparent very easily.
I appreciated them the backlog they could give me input etc.
so but I could do it because I was I was in charge.
and I really understood that when I left the company that not many people are.
when they encounter scrum especially when you're a developer or a project manager or a team lead. are able to make that change. and you have to convince your manager.
but how do you convince your manager because he doesn't read this big thick books on offer for software engineers.
and because it's full of technical issues and he doesn't really understand it etc.
so I thought well I should have something that you can read on the plane.
which and even which is a book.
but you also when you just browse it through you can get a main message and you get the understanding.
and that's when we came up with the idea of a novel.
and then of course Jeff and an Elko also joined in working working on on that.
and that that it became a story which you can read in two to three hours on a plane.
when you when you fly across the Atlantic or something.
and then you can understand the complete idea behind scrum on a well a story way.
so it's it's a low threshold to to to start to understand it.
and there are there streamers in the book with these quotes which give you the main messages.
it has a one-page summary at the end of each chapter.
and it even has a one-page summary of scrum on the end of the book.
so even a manager who has only 5 to 10 minutes time will understand the core concepts of scrum.
and that helps developers you know to sell them.
because it they tend to talk about let's say the mechanics.
they tend to talk to the manager about you know the planning meeting then we need a product owner.
and then then these managers what all these terminology all these changes that it's that's much too difficult.
but if you let's say put it put it down to the basics you say well what would you like.
if he if it would be never late.
and how would you like it when we always deliver the highest value first.
or how would you like it when there's a change coming from the fields.
that we're able to deal with that within two weeks.
that always convinces management.
and that's the story what we should tell.
and that's let's say in the power of scrum of the book is an approach for a management and a management level.
and of course it's also good because of that force of engineers to understand what it is.
but really to convince a management level where the power of scrum is yes is really good.
and it's also translated into many languages right?
yeah, yeah, we originally brought it out in in in Dutch.
it's about a year ago we brought that in in in Dutch. we have forward by Jeff.
that has sold something like ten thousand copies at the moment which is really huge.
every of a small country well we have only with sixty million people.
so I think the the the the software engineering population.
I'm not sure about the figures but let's say this one somewhere between hundred and two hundred thousand or something.
III would estimate we saw ten thousands of the book.
and it's now also out in in in Germany by henning both female the German edit.
and Guillaume Buddha made the French edit in in France.
and now for the international version English version as Jeff Sutherland did the major rewrite of the of the book.
and I must say that it's it's it's especially the novelist character of the book is so largely improved.
that I'm really proud of what it is.
and in fact I'm tempted to rewrite a Dutch version again based on the English version.
the way changed the way it's made better.
cool, sounds really good.
yeah, and actually it's even nice to tell you maybe that we even even taped a professional movie about about it together with Jeff.
which is oh wow.
yeah, yeah, which is a scrum master master movie.
it's a kind of movie that you say well this is very big guy scrum master.
who who punishes everybody who dilates the scrum scrum rules.
but you know I will put a link together if the if the if the podcaster people can look at this.
is free for funny movie with and Jeff is even playing a major part in the book movie.
great, I'm looking forward to seeing it.
cool, so I think we I think we covered most of our topics um.
do you think you have any other pearls of wisdom you would like to share with our listeners at the end of this episode?
yeah, well I think you know we've talked about this development.
we talked about distributed scrum.
we talked about let's say some of the mechanics or the problems to overcome.
I think let's say and then we addressed it merely in in the talk already.
but I think that the key change or the key answer is in perception.
and with technical people now we we like to think about solutions.
that's always when we are in meetings with software engineers or software engineering managers.
we are we are discussing solutions but we're hardly discussing the problem.
so let alone the problem behind the problem.
and I think most of the challenge is a distributed software engineering or distributor scrum.
are caused by distance and by the effects of the distance.
but distance is let's say a physical thing.
but this is not the the physical distance or the language is it's the perception of it.
and if we look to the research and look at the work that we can be doing.
you have a large influence and a perception of distance you hadn't.
you can have a large impact on the presence of awareness of people that are working together.
so I think that the answer for distributed development and disabuse it's scrum.
really lies in perception of distance.
and all kinds of dueling and all kinds of solutions and attitudes and training.
can be thought of and are currently available that can help really fluency perception.
because if the perception of distance is beyond leaders.
but this is not known it's no longer a problem.
and that's why I'm also such a fan and promoting.
and that's why I'm really researching the effectiveness of Chicago.
it's because that is exactly within the field that is the main vision is that we have is.
when we reduce the perception of distance we are solving the major problem in distributed and in Global's of Engineering.
great, really thank you very very much for being with us today. thank you for asking me to join you.
yeah, it was a pleasure and I hope to see you next time soon. okay, fine, thanks.
thank you all right bye.
thanks for listening to software engineering radio.
as a radio is an educational program brought to you by hillside Europe.
if you want more information about the podcast and the other episodes.
visit our website at SE - radio dotnet.
if you want to support us you can donate to the SA radio team via the website.
or you can advertise for sa radio for example by clicking on the Digg.
reddit delicious and slashed up buttons or by talking about us on Twitter and Facebook.
you can also support us by joining team and shouldering some of the work.
to contact the team please send email to team at se - radio Matt.
or if your feedback is specific to an episode please use the comments facility on the website.
so other people can react to your comments.
this episode of SU radio as well as all other episodes are licensed under a creative commons 2.5 license.
please see the website for details.
[Music]